Institute of Physics
Pontificia Universidad Católica
Av. Vicuña Mackenna 4860, Santiago

☎ 56.2.2354.9728

⋈ rodsoto@uc.cl

Rodrigo Soto Garrido

Research and Teaching Interests

Teaching: Teaching and innovation in Physics and Engineering courses.

Research: Strongly correlated systems, unconventional superconductivity, topological phases of matter, one dimensional systems, connections of high-enery physics and condensed matter physics (such as holography) and statistical models.

Education

- 2015 **Ph.D. in Physics**, *U. of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign*.
 - Thesis: Pair Density Wave Superconducting States and Statistical Mechanics of Dimers. Advisor: Eduardo Fradkin.
- 2009 Master's degree in Physics, U. Técnica Federico Santa María.
 - Thesis: Metastable magnetic states in the triangular-lattice. Advisor: Patricio Vargas.
- 2009 Professional degree in Civil Engineering (with honors), Egresado in 2007 ranked 1/55, U. Técnica Federico Santa María.

Experience

- 2019- Assistant Professor, Inst. of Physics, Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile.
 - Courses: Electricity and Magnetism, Statics and Dynamics, Classical Mechanics II.
- 2015-2019 Assistant Professor, Universidad San Sebastián.
 - Courses: Electricity and Magnetism, Hydraulics, Mechanics of Solids, Structural Analysis and Fluid Mechanics.
- 2015-2019 Lecturer in Physics, Inst. of Physics, Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile.
 - Part time lecturer in Physics: Electricity and Magnetism, Statics and Dynamics.
- 2010–2015 Graduate Research Assistant, Dept. of Physics, U. of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.
 - Research in Theoretical Condensed Matter Physics and Mathematical Physics.
 - Preparation of technical publications and presentation of main results at conferences.
- 2009–2015 Graduate Teaching Assistant, Dept. of Physics, U. of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.
 - Teaching assistant for different courses in undergraduate and graduate physics. These include: Advanced Field Theory, Relativity and Math applications, Electromagnetism, Classical Mechanics.
 - 2009 Lecturer in Physics, Dept. of Physics, U. Técnica Federico Santa María.
 - Part time lecturer in Physics: Introduction to Physics.
- 2003-2009 Teaching Assistant, Dept. of Physics, U. Técnica Federico Santa María.
 - Teaching assistant for different courses in undergraduate and graduate physics. These include: Quantum Mechanics, Statistical Mechanics, Solid State Physics, General Physics I: Mechanics.
 - Teaching assistant coordinator for General Physics I: Mechanics

- 2004-2006 Undergraduate Research Assistant, Dept. of Physics, U. Técnica Federico Santa María.
 - Assistance in the fabrication and characterization of Carbon Nanotubes in Patricio Häberle's group.

Languages

Spanish Native

English Full professional proficiency

Computer skills

Software Mathematica, Matlab, Python, Fortran

Awards

- 2010 Ismael Valdés Valdés Award, Instituto de Ingenieros (Chilean Institute of Engineers).
- 2009 **Becas Chile Scholarship**, Chile's National Commission for Scientific and Technological Research (CONICYT).
- 2007 **Postgraduate Studies Scholarship**, Chile's National Commission for Scientific and Technological Research (CONICYT).
- 2004 Núcleo Milenio Undergraduate Research Scholarship.

Others: Selected for the Phi Kappa Phi (selects top 10% grad students) and Tau Beta Pi honor societies. Several travel awards, cuadro de honor (USM), Programa Incentivo a la Iniciación Científica (2008, USM)

Grants

- 2020 FONDECYT Regular, Principal Investigator, Grant Number 1200399.
 - Title: Field Theories and Holography in Quantum Matter
- 2019 ANID PIA Anillo, Associate Investigator, Grant Number ACT192023.
 - Title: Light-Matter Interactions in Topological Nanomaterials: Towards low-consumption Information Technology
- 2019 FONDECYT Regular, Coinvestigator, Grant Number 1190361.
 - Title: Manybody Physics in Topological Materials
- 2016 **FONDECYT Iniciación en Investigación**, *Principal Investigator*, Grant Number 11160542.
 - Title: Strongly Correlated Systems in Condensed Matter Physics

Publications

- 2020 Vladimir Juričić, Ignacio Salazar Landea and **Rodrigo Soto-Garrido**. Phase transitions in a holographic multi-Weyl semimetal. Journal of High Energy Physics **06**(2020), 200
- 2020 Julian May-Mann, Ryan Levy, Rodrigo Soto-Garrido, Gil Young Cho, Brian K. Clark and Eduardo Fradkin. Topology and the one-dimensional Kondo-Heisenberg model. Phys. Rev. B 101, 165133
- 2020 Rodrigo Soto-Garrido, Enrique Muñoz and Vladimir Juričić. Dislocation defect as a bulk probe of monopole charge of multi-Weyl semimetals. Phys. Rev. Research 2, 012043(R), Editor's Suggestion
- 2019 Enrique Muñoz and **Rodrigo Soto-Garrido**. Thermoelectric transport in torsional strained Weyl semimetals J. Appl. Phys. **125**, 082507

- 2019 Guillermo Fuertes, Manuel Vargas, Miguel Alfaro, **Rodrigo Soto-Garrido**, Jorge Sabattin and María Alejandra Peralta. Chaotic Genetic Algorithm and The Effects of Entropy in Performance Optimization. Chaos **29**, 013132
- 2018 Gastón Giordano, Nicolás Grandi, Adrián Lugo and Rodrigo Soto-Garrido. Strange metal crossover in the doped holographic superconductor. Journal of High Energy Physics 10(2018), 068
- 2018 Rodrigo Soto-Garrido and Enrique Muñoz. Electronic transport in torsional strained Weyl semimetals. J. Phys.: Condens. Matter 30, 195302
- 2017 Rodrigo Soto-Garrido, Yuxuan Wang, Eduardo Fradkin and S. Lance Cooper. Higgs Modes in the Pair Density Wave Superconducting State. Phys. Rev. B 95, 214502
- 2017 Enrique Muñoz and Rodrigo Soto-Garrido. Analytic approach to magneto-strain tuning of electronic transport through a graphene nanobubble: Perspectives for a strain sensor J. Phys.: Condens. Matter 29, 445302
- 2015 **Rodrigo Soto-Garrido**, Gil Young Cho, and Eduardo Fradkin. Quasi-one-dimensional pair density wave superconducting state. Phys. Rev. B **91**, 195102
- 2014 Gil Young Cho, Rodrigo Soto-Garrido and Eduardo Fradkin. Topological Pair-Density-Wave Superconducting States Phys. Rev. Lett. 113, 256405
- 2014 Rodrigo Soto-Garrido and Eduardo Fradkin. Pair-density-wave superconducting states and electronic liquid-crystal phases. Phys. Rev. B 89, 165126
- 2014 Philippe Di Francesco and Rodrigo Soto-Garrido. Arctic curves of the octahedron equation.
 J. Phys. A: Math. Theor. 47, 285204. IOP Select
- 2009 P. Landeros, P. R. Guzmán, R. Soto-Garrido and J Escrig. Magnetostatic fields in tubular nanostructures. J. Phys. D: Appl. Phys. 42, 225002
- 2009 **R. Soto**, G. Martínez, M. N. Baibich, J. M. Florez, and P. Vargas. Metastable states in the triangular-lattice Ising model studied by Monte Carlo simulations: Application to the spin-chain compound Ca₃Co₂O₆. Phys. Rev. B **79**, 184422
- 2006 Rodrigo Segura, Wladimir Ibáñez, **Rodrigo Soto**, Samuel Hevia, and Patricio Häberle. Growth Morphology and Spectroscopy of Multiwalled Carbon Nanotubes synthesized by pyrolisis of Iron Phthalocyanine. J. Nanosci. Nanotechnol., Vol. **6**, No. 7

Conferences, Programs, and Talks

- 2020 American Physical Society March Meeting, Contributed Talk, Denver, Co. USA.
- 2019 American Physical Society March Meeting, Contributed Talk, Boston, MA USA.
- 2019 Colloquium Institute of Physics, Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile, Invited talk. Santiago, Chile.
- 2018 Engineering and Sciences, Universidad Adolfo Ibáñez, Invited talk. Santiago, Chile.
- 2018 Strings, Higher Spins and Dualities, Invited Talk. Pucón, Chile.
- 2018 American Physical Society March Meeting, Contributed Talk, Los Angeles, CA USA.
- 2018 Department of Physics, Universidad Andrés Bello, Invited talk. Santiago, Chile.
- 2017 American Physical Society March Meeting, Contributed Talk, New Orleans, LA USA.
- 2016 Meeting on Theoretical Physics, Universidad San Sebastián, Invited talk. Valdivia, Chile.
- 2016 **Seminario de Educación**, Universidad Autónoma Gabriel René Moreno, Invited talk. Santa Cruz, Bolivia.
- 2016 Workshop Los Andes Spintrónicos, Universidad de Chile, Invited talk. Santiago, Chile.
- 2016 Colloquium Institute of Physics, Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile, Invited talk. Santiago, Chile.
- 2015 **Condensed Matter Seminar**, Universidad Técnica Federico Santa María, Invited talk. Santiago, Chile.
- 2015 American Physical Society March Meeting, Contributed Talk, San Antonio, TX USA.

- 2014 Integrability and Representation Theory Seminar, Math Seminar UIUC, Invited talk, Urbana, IL. USA.
- 2014 Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics, Conference on Discrete Mathematics, Symposium invited talk, Minneapolis, MN. USA.
- 2014 Center for Emergent Superconductivity Workshop, Urbana, IL. USA.
- 2014 Entangled Quantum Matter and Topology Workshop, Urbana, IL. USA.
- 2014 Workshop on Strongly Correlated Electron Systems at 60 years old, Urbana, IL. USA.
- 2014 American Physical Society March Meeting, Contributed Talk, Denver, Co. USA.
- 2013 American Physical Society March Meeting, Contributed Talk, Baltimore, MD. USA.
- 2013 Theory Winter School, Unconventional Superconductivity, Tallahassee, FL. USA.
- 2012 Workshop on Topology, Entanglement and Strong Correlations in Condensed Matter, *Urbana*, *IL. USA*.
- 2012 American Physical Society March Meeting, Contributed Talk, Boston, MA. USA.
- 2008 International Centre For Theoretical Physics Winter School, Micro and Nano photonics For Life Sciences, Trieste, Italy.
- 2008 Simposio Chileno de Física, Valparaíso, Chile.